Guide to the Louise Degn broadcast journalism audio-visual collection 1969-2007
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
- KSL-TV news stories - Louise Degn, reporter, 1970-1971; 2002; DVD (Disc 2)
  - Coalville Tabernacle 4 story, 1971 March 03 (Video 18)
    Louise Degn's note: Viewing the stand-up with 30 years of hind-sight, I think it is biased and one-sided. The stand-up did not run in the 6pm version of the story, however I showed it to my supervisor (Ted Capener) before editing it into the 10pm version. He advised against using it, but said I could if I wanted to. So I did. The story angered Church leaders who thought their own station had betrayed them. By Friday, their displeasure had rumbled down through the hierarchy to my supervisor who sternly reprimanded me. Specifically, he asked why I had neglected to include the statement issued on Wednesday (the day of the demolition) by the First Presidency of the LDS Church. I had seen the statement on the newswire but had dismissed it because it contained no new information. I have since learned in my journalism career that the fact that a statement is issued is news itself, regardless of the content. Historical Note: The building in the background of the Fitzen interview is the three-story Bank of Utah building on the southwest corner of State and South Temple, which was later torn down. Original script available.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 4 additional film, 1971 March 03 (Video 19)
    Demolition. 03:36.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 4 additional film, 1971 March 03 (Video 20)
    Demolition, sheriff interview. 01:10.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 5, 1971 March 03 (Video 21)
    Aftermath. 02:42.
  - Wurlitzer Wigwam, 1971 March 16 (Video 22)
    A new piano manufacturing plant in Logan pollutes the air. 01:45.
    Louise Degn's note: I got into trouble with this story too. The Wurlitzer people called my supervisor, Ted Capener, and said that I'd been trespassing on their property. I thought I was just doing what I'd been assigned--covering a controversial issue in Logan. Wurlitzer had declined to be interviewed, so I'd just gotten the story without them. After two controversial stories, Ted was probably glad that I left the newsroom during the spring of that year to finish my Master's Degree at Northwestern University. Technical Note: The video flutter at the beginning of the story was caused by broken sprocket holes on the original film while it was being transferred to video for this 2002 reconstruction. The original voice track of this story was lost and has been rerecorded for this 2002 reconstruction. Original script available.
  - Weight Watchers, 1971 June (Video 23)
    Founder of the diet business, Jean Nidetch, visits Salt Lake City. 01:32.
    Louise Degn's note: At the time, Weight Watchers was becoming very popular throughout the country. It began a trend in commercial weight-loss businesses. It is interesting to note the Salt Lake City scenes in the background. In the first section of film you can see the Walgreen Drug store, a five or six story building located on the southwest corner of Main and South Temple. As Jean Nidetch walks in front of the Hotel Utah (now the Joseph Smith Memorial Building), in the background you can see cars driving along Main Street between North and South Temple, a block that was permanently closed to traffic in 1999. In the second section of silent film, you can see the old ZCMI department store building with its series of mini shops facing the street. The building was replaced by an indoor mall. Original audio track and script are missing. The A roll only is available.
  - Hitchhiking story, 1971 August (Video 24)
    A new fad of young people hitchhiking across America. 02:57.
    Louise Degn's note: The audio on this story is difficult to hear. I think it was OK when the story was originally broadcast but got distorted during the film-to-tape transfer for this reconstruction. To assist clarity, I transcribed the first section of audio onto the screen. This was NOT done for the original story, however. Original handwritten script available.
  - Hitchhiking additional film, 1971 August (Video 25)
    00:40.
  - Spiral Jetty, 1971 August (Video 26)
    A new Robert Smithson sculpture in the Great Salt Lake off Promontory Point. 02:02.
    Louise Degn's note: The film was shot on a silent film camera. The aerials were shot from the KSL traffic airplane, which means the pilot and photographer was probably Jack Ford. The sounds of the airplane and the lake were recorded on audio tape separately and mixed with the reporter narration. Several years later I did another story on another piece of earth sculpture, Sun Tunnels, installed north of Wendover. Sun Tunnels was created by Smithson's widow, Nacy Holt. She made the tunnels at a plant in Lehi and let me take home one of the concrete cores removed to make the "stars" in each of the constellations. I sealed the "star" with a shiny goop and used it as a doorstop in my home for years. Original script available.
  - Renaissance Fair, 1971 September 06 (Video 27)
    Utah Art League sponsors a fair in East Canyon. 01:56.
    Louise Degn's note: Film for the first part of the story is missing. Original script available.
  - H. L. Hunt interview, circa 1970-1971 (Video 28)
    The Texas oil billionaire visits Salt Lake City. 01:36.
- KSL-TV news documentary - Louise Degn, reporter, 1970; DVD (Disc 3)
  - In whose land, 1970 December 26 (Video 1)
    Israeli/Palestinian conflic. 30:00.
- WBBM and KSL news stories - Louise Degn, reporter, 1972-1977; DVD (Disc 4)
  - Housewares (WBBM), 1972 January 20 (Video 1)
    Manufacturers' trade show at McCormick Place, Chicago. 01:35.
  - Chicago blues musicians (WBBM) story, 1972 February 03 (Video 2)
    Sam Chatman and Walter Vincent. 01:43.
  - Chicago blues musicians (WBBM) additional film, 1972 February 03 (Video 3)
    00:47.
  - Cowboys in Daniels Canyon, 1976 March 12 (Video 4)
    Bill Ecker and Tom Davis ride horseback from Texas to Alaska. 01:40.
  - Body painting at May Fest, 1976 May 05 (Video 5)
    2nd annual body painting festival at the University of Utah. 01:18.
  - Navajo rug weaver, 1976 May 20 (Video 6)
    Rose Keith of Blanding, Utah, traditional rug weaver. 01:40.
  - Crickets and seagulls, 1976 July 23 (Video 7)
    Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (LDS) historian Glen Leonard explores myths about pioneer story. 02:03.
  - Capitol Theatre organ renovation, 1976 July 31 (Video 8)
    Renovation of 1927 Wurlitzer organ played by Mike Ohman. 02:13.
  - Melvin Dummar - Howard Hughes' will (bad video), 1976 December 28 (Video 9)
    Year-end summary of story. 02:47.
  - Ice Capade skater, 1977 April 23 (Video 10)
    Profile of chorus skater Judy Roof. 01:48.
  - Allred murders, 1977 May 11 (Video 11)
    Polygamist leader Rulon Allred is assassinated 05:53.
    Louise Degn's note: Late afternoon May 10, 1977, the KSL assignment person heard on the police scanner about a murder in Murray City and asked me to go on it. She had no additional information. While driving there, John Hollenhorst, another reporter, called on the two-way to say the victim might be a polygamist, a member of the "Church of the Lamb of God." We arrived in time to get film of the body being wheeled to the ambulance. A group of very distraught people was standing outside the one-story, brick medical clinic where a Dr. Rulon Allred had been shot. In 1977 polygamists were left alone by the authorities, following the bad publicity of the "Short Creek" raids in the 1950s. They lived hidden among the larger society. I approached the group. "I understand he was a member of the Church of the Lamb of God." One man shot back, angrily yelling, "Them's the ones that did it!" That was the first indication to the general public of the feud among the polygamy groups. I talked more with them and returned the next day to interview a friend, William Baird, and Nephi Allred, Dr. Allred's son. The group's initial reaction was right. Ervil LeBaron, leader of the Church of the Lamb of God, eventually was convicted of this murder, as well as others, in his bloody fight for sole control of the polygamy groups.
  - Piano festival at BYU, 1977 July 02 (Video 12)
    Concert pianist Lili Krause instructs students at Brigham Young University (BYU). 01:48.
  - Park City Arts Festival, 1977 August 20 (Video 13)
    7th annual festival on Main Street. 01:54.
- KSL news stories - Louise Degn, reporter, 1976-1977; DVD (Disc 5)
  - Capital punishment promo, 1976 November (Video 1)
    This series ran prior to Gary Gillmore's execution on 17 January 1977. 00:30.
  - Capital punishment 1, 1976 November 21 (Video 2)
    History of Utah capital punishment law (Ed Yeates, reporter). 01:37.
  - Capital punishment 2, 1976 November 22 (Video 3)
    Executions of John D. Lee, Don Jesse Neil, Joe Hill. (Ed Yeates, reporter). 02:14.
  - Capital punishment 3, 1976 November 22 (Video 4)
    Methods of execution. (Ed Yeates, reporter). 01:55.
  - Capital punishment 4, 1976 November 24 (Video 5)
    Voice of Gary Gillmore explaining his decision to be executed. 01:32.
  - Capital punishment 5, 1976 November 25 (Video 6)
    Moral and religious views on capital punishment. Interview: Monsignor W. H. McDougall, Catholic Diocese. 02:35.
  - Capital punishment 6, 1976 November 26 (Video 7)
    Execution as a deterrent to crime. 02:02.
  - Great Salt Lake flooding 1, 1977 January 16 (Video 8)
    History of changing lake levels. 01:45.
  - Great Salt Lake flooding 2, 1977 January 17 (Video 9)
    What is threatened by rising lake level. 01:47.
  - Great Salt Lake flooding 3, 1977 January 18 (Video 10)
    Proposed solutions to control lake level. 02:18.
  - Great Salt Lake flooding 4, 1977 January 19 (Video 11)
    Arguments for breaching Southern Pacific causeway. 02:15.
  - Great Salt Lake flooding 5, 1977 January 20 (Video 12)
    Arguments against breaching Southern Pacific causeway. 02:03.
  - Great Salt Lake flooding 6, 1977 January 21 (Video 13)
    Forecasting lake level. 01:51.
  - TV violence 1, 1977 February 28 (Video 14)
    Harmful effects of violent TV shows. 02:03.
  - TV violence 2, 1977 March 01 (Video 15)
    Beneficial effects of pro-social TV shows. 01:53.
  - TV violence 3, 1977 March 02 (Video 16)
    Influencing TV programming with product boycotts. 01:53.
  - TV violence 4, 1977 March 03 (Video 17)
    Groups trying to influence TV programming. 01:53.
  - TV violence 5, 1977 March 04 (Video 18)
    Lynn Scoresby family regulates TV viewing. 02:04.
  - Migrant workers 1, 1976 September 06 (Video 19)
    Profile of Luciano Hernandez Family. 01:13.
  - Migrant workers 2, 1976 September 07 (Video 20)
    Health care for migrant families. Interview: John Steven Lujan, Utah Migrant Council. 01:34.
  - Migrant workers 3, 1976 September 08 (Video 21)
    Job training for children of migrant families. Interview: Frank Vidaurii, Migrant Worker. 01:24.
  - Migrant workers 4, 1976 September 09 (Video 22)
    Legal status of migrant workers. Interview: Gerald D. Fasbender, United States Immigration Service. 01:34.
- KSL news stories: Teton Dam break - Louise Degn, reporter, 1976-1978; DVD (Disc 6)
  - Teton Dam break special report, 1976 June 06 (Video 1)
    11:00.
    Louise Degn's note: On Saturday, 05 June 1976, I was working in the newsroom and received a telephone call from a woman saying she had relatives in Idaho and heard the Teton Dam had broken. I had no idea what or where that was so I got out an Idaho map and determined what county that was in and called the sheriff's office. The officer who answered said, yes, there was a small break in the dam but it was not serious. I put that sound bite on KSL Radio news. Shortly -- I can't recall how we knew -- we discovered it was more serious so we decided to go up. Bob Greenwell, the photographer, was also a pilot, so he rented a small plane and we flew to Idaho landing in a cornfield. We thumbed our way around the area, interviewing people and shooting film of the flood. We waded into one street, not knowing where we were, and shouted to a man, "What street is this?" "Main Street," he answered., so that's where I did my stand-up. Taking off in the plane on the cornfield dirt road was harrowing. Bob later told me that we cleared a fence at the end of the field by just feet. We flew around the area and using an aviation map I could pinpoint exact towns that were under water and those that were safe. That type of exact information is crucial to people with loved ones in the area and the very information that is often lacking in the initial news reports of disasters. We got back to the station by 10 p.m., splattered in mud and soaked with floodwater and I went on the air with a report, the only Utah station to have original on-the-ground pictures. The people we interviewed that day were the ones we did follow-up reports with at six months and two years.
  - Teton Dam break - Blackfoot, Idaho, 1976 June 07 (Video 2)
    03:47.
  - Teton Dam break - Idaho Falls, Firth, Blackfoot, Rexburg, 1976 June 07 (Video 3)
    04:00.
  - Teton Dam break 6 month follow-up 1, 1976 December 05 (Video 4)
    Reconstruction of homes in Sugar City. 02:50.
  - Teton Dam break 6 month follow-up 2, 1976 December 06 (Video 5)
    Reconstruction of buildings in Sugar City. 02:10.
  - Teton Dam break 6 month follow-up 3, 1976 December 06 (Video 6)
    Reconstruction in Rexburg. 01:34.
  - Teton Dam break 6 month follow-up 4, 1976 December 06 (Video 7)
    Mr. and Mrs. Glen Walters Family. 02:50.
  - Teton Dam break 6 month follow-up 5, 1976 December 07 (Video 8)
    Reconstruction of farm land. Brent Barrus. 01:33.
  - Teton Dam break year end summary, 1976 December 31 (Video 9)
  - Teton Dam break 2 year follow-up, 1978 June 04 (Video 9)
    03:35.
- KSL news stories: Maurice Abravanel and Utah Symphony - Louise Degn, reporter, 1970-1979; DVD (Disc 7)
  - Utah Symphony, 1976 June 06 (Video 1)
    Recordings postponed due to low record sales. 01:23.
  - Beverly Sills, soprano, 1977 May 23 (Video 2)
    Abravanel 75th birthday concert. 01:40.
  - Acoustics of new (Abravanel) Symphony Hall, 1979 September 15 (Video 3)
    Interview with acoustician Cyril M. Harris. 06:10.
  - The Maestro, Utah Symphony conductor Maurice Abravanel, 1978 January 07 (Video 4)
    09:00.
  - Abravanel rehearsing Mahler 2nd Symphony unedited film, 1977 December (Video 5)
    05:32.
  - Abravanel conducting Mahler 2nd Symphony in Tabernacle unedited film, 1977 December 09 (Video 6)
    08:11.
- KSL news stories and documentary: Ballet West - Louise Degn, reporter, 1978-1982; DVD (Disc 8)
  - "The Lark Ascending" based on music by Ralph Vaughan Williams, circa 1978-1979 (Video 1)
    Ballet West performs in Cedar City. Unedited film. 04:04.
  - Inside the turning point, 1978 February 04 (Video 2)
    Profile of Ballet West principal dancer, Victoria Morgan, and choreographer, Bruce Marks. Premier of "Sanctus." 07:50.
  - Ballet West backstage, 1982 March 16 (Video 3)
    Behind the scenes life of ballet dancers Lee Provancha Day, Bruce Caldwell, Lisa LaManna and Wendi Beckwitt. 24:40.
- KSL Dimension Five stories - Louise Degn, reporter, 1977-1978; DVD (Disc 9)
  - My brother the magician, 1977 October 21 (Video 1)
    Ralph G. Degn entertains children with magic. 05:38.
  - Bubble house, 1977 November 19 (Video 2)
    Energy efficient house built below ground in Utah County. 04:37.
  - International Women's Year, 1977 November 26 (Video 3)
    Controversial national women's rights convention, Houston, Texas. 11:08.
    Louise Degn's note: One of the most contentious social issues of 1970s was the role of women in society. The United Nations declared 1977 as International Women's Year (IWY). President Carter appointed a commission to plan a National Women's Conference in Houston, Texas, November 18 to 21, 1977, and to propose a National Plan of Action, which included controversial issues like abortion, sexual preference, the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA), and day care. Leading up to Houston, each state held its own conference. Utah's erupted in controversy when the Mormon Church urged its women to attend in large numbers and resist passage of liberal social ideas. The mainly Mormon women elected their own slate of conservative delegates to the Houston meeting, while the organizers appointed its own slate of liberal members. Thus, two slates of Utah delegates, with opposing points of view, represented Utah: Elected (conservative) and Appointed (liberal).
  - T-bone on the rocks, 1978 February 18 (Video 4)
    Caterers serve dinner on Snow Basin's ski slopes. 02:24.
  - Soldier Summit lineman, 1978 February 25 (Video 5)
    Copper lines still carry phone calls to rural Utah. 05:13.
  - Mick Boyle series, 1978 April 17-22 (Video 6)
    Quadriplegic graduates from BYU Law School. 16:00.
    Louise Degn's note: Since these stories Mindy and Mick divorced a few years after his accident. He married Cheryl Chandler Smith in 1982. They had a daughter, Sydney, and adopted twins from El Salvador—son McKay and daughter McKenzie. Mick practiced personal injury and discrimination law in Salt Lake and spent many hours counseling newly injured paraplegic patients. He died suddenly March 3, 1991, of acute pneumonia, his lungs weakened from his injuries.
  - Bloopers, 1978 June 10 (Video 7)
    Out-takes of mistakes by KSL reporters. 01:34.
  - Opera house in the desert, 1978 November 11 (Video 8)
    Dancer Marta Becket runs a theater in Death Valley. 07:21.
  - Ice skater story, 1978 December 23 (Video 9)
    Louise Degn skates on Beus Pond in Ogden, UT. 01:48.
  - Ice skater additional film, 1978 December 23 (Video 10)
    07:23.
- KSL Dimension Five stories - Louise Degn, reporter, 1979-1980; DVD (Disc 10)
  - Juanita Brooks, 1979 March 17 (Video 1)
    Utah historian of the 1857 Mountain Meadows Massacre. 12:48.
    Louise Degn's note: Juanita Brooks (1898-1989). The story was filmed ten years before she died in 1989. She was, however, already suffering from dementia. I knew her time was short and wanted to do an interview before it was too late. At times she was lucid, other times not, so we had to shoot more film than usual and edit extensively. She was most alert remembering the past. Outside the high school in Mesquite, Nevada, recalling the beginnings of her book, she came alive. Clearly, this had been one of the most important events of her life.
  - Death Valley burros, 1979 October 06 (Video 2)
    Burro adoption program in Death Valley, California. 07:01.
  - Tina Gunn, 1980 February 23 (Video 3)
    BYU women's basketball star sets national scoring records. 10:49.
    Louise Degn's note: This story was one of the first shot on 3/4-inch analog videotape. Video editing made quick cuts, freeze frames, and other effects easier to do than with film.
  - Untaming the wild, 1980 March 22 (Video 4)
    A way-station for unwanted wild animals. 07:45.
  - Anthon Transcript, 1980 May 24 (Video 5)
    Forger Mark Hofmann's first historic Mormon document. 12:00.
    Mark Hofmann was a master forger of historic Mormon and other American documents, fooling experts across the country. The Anthon Transcript was his first big "discovery." When I did this story, Hofmann was reluctant to be interviewed on camera. His speech was flat and controlled. I thought he was just a young, shy university student. Later, of course, I understood he worked hard to mask his emotions and the truth. When Hofmann's schemes started to unravel, he resorted to murder. On 15 October 1985 a bomb killed document collector Steven Christensen, and another killed Kathleen Sheets, wife of a Christensen business associate. The next day a third bomb injured Hofmann himself, while he was parked in his car near Church headquarters. I excitedly told the news director we had footage of the "victim," which we ran on the news that night. A viewer at home saw it, called us and said she'd seen that person riding the elevator in Christensen's building shortly before the first bomb. We ran the interview that night. Hofmann's lawyers subpoenaed the news story arguing it tainted the witness's testimony and a potential jury. Both issues became moot when Hofmann pled guilty and was sentenced to life in prison.
  - Dimension Five prom, 1980 August 24 (Video 6)
    00:30.
- KSL news documentary - Louise Degn, reporter, 1979; DVD (Disc 11)
  - Original cancellation of "Mormon Women and Depression", 1978 November 11 (Video 1)
    On-air announcement of cancellation of original documentary. 00:40.
    Louise Degn's note: The documentary "Mormon Women and Depression" was originally scheduled for broadcast on 11 November 1978. Station management, however, pulled the program after receiving objections from leaders of the LDS Church Relief Society. The cancellation of the heavily promoted documentary generated hundreds of protest letters and calls. Station management replied the program had been pulled for revision, not cancellation. The controversy opened many doors for further interviews, and the program was expanded from a half-hour to one-hour and, in my opinion, became a much better program. The final version aired three months later on 17 February 1979. It generated hundreds of requests for copies to show at church functions around the world and won the National Reporting Award from the American Mental Health Association. Original Cancellation is the disclaimer which ran before the show on the original air date and the show open which announces the program content which replaced it.
  - Iris Award, 1980 March 22 (Video 2)
    Given to Depression Series by the National Association of TV Program Executives. 03:08.
  - Mormon women and depression, 1980 March 22 (Video 3)
    Also known as: Three faces of Depression, the Woman. 1:00:00.
- KSL news documentary - Louise Degn, reporter, 1979; DVD (Disc 12)
  - Bedroom births, 1979 November 17 (Video 1)
    Three ways of giving birth--home, hospital, birthing room. 27:50.
- KSL news stories and music videos - Louise Degn, reporter, 1983-1991; DVD (Disc 13)
  - Manti Temple, 1983 August 25 (Video 1)
    Refurbishing Mormon temple. 04:23.
  - Violin School mural, 1983 December 10 (Video 2)
    Blaine DeMille paints mural on Prier Violin Making School. 01:33.
  - Gypsy nuns, 1984 January 06 (Video 3)
    Catholic nuns serve in southern Utah. 06:01.
  - Montreaux, 1984 April 12 (Video 4)
    New Age musicians perform. 06:01.
  - Harriet Tubman music video, 1984 May 15 (Video 5)
    Music video about heroine of the underground railroad. 03:17.
  - Liz Story, 1986 April 14 (Video 6)
    New Age pianist/composer. 21:25.
  - I Cried music video, 1988 February 23 (Video 7)
    Music video about divorce. Sam Prigg, photographer. 02:38.
  - Pioneer Day Parade highlights, 1991 July 24 (Video 8)
    Celebrations of Utah's Pioneer Day. 05:00.
    Louise Degn's note: For many years KSL had broadcast the Days of 47 Parade. In 1990, I was producing a noontime program, "Midday." The anchor, Bruce Lindsay, suggested we stay on the air through our program and broadcast other holiday events. Live broadcasting was still rather chancy in 1990, but we took up the challenge. We were on the air five hours, in many locations around the state. The next year, 1991, I returned to produce this event again.
- KSL news, Maggie Smith essays and cooking - Louise Degn, producer, 1984; 1986; DVD (Disc 14)
  - Maggie Smith obituary, 1986 January 28 (Video 1)
    01:14.